Finding Aid for Macomb-Oakland Regional Center Records 1972-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Macomb-Oakland Regional Center Records 1972-2001, 1972-1989
Macomb-Oakland Regional Center.
4 linear feet
Non-profit human services agency established in 1972 and concerned with the placement of people with developmental and psychiatric disabilities within the local community and the problems resulting from the closing of state institutions in Michigan. The record group includes administrative and publicity files; subject files relating to community placement and resistance to the placement of group homes in Michigan cities and towns; and videocassettes.
0139 Bf 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Macomb-Oakland Regional Center (Donor no. 9036 ) in November 2000 and January 2001.
The record group is open for research.
The Macomb-Oakland Regional Center, Inc. (MORC) is a private non-profit human services agency. Established in 1972, MORC has been a leader in assisting people with developmental and psychiatric disabilities who have chosen to live in the community instead of in institutions, nursing homes, or with their families. MORC's mission statement states that the organization is "dedicated to serving men, women, and children with differing abilities so they may, as true citizens, celebrate life, freedom, and independence in the community." Many of the people served by MORC have challenging needs; nearly all have disabilities which substantially impair life functions and have limited resources available to them. MORC provides support and housing for people with developmental and psychiatric disabilities, respite care for people with developmental disabilities, and general rehabilitation services. In October 2000 MORC provided services for more than 4,500 people with a variety of disabilities.
The original MORC facility was conceived as a traditional facility called the Macomb Oakland Regional Retardation Center and designed to provide housing for 650 people. The 1970s and 1980s, however, saw a growing trend toward placing people with developmental disabilities in "group homes" within the community. Proponents of this new model of supporting the disabled argued that people with disabilities have the legal right to live in the least restrictive environment possible, and that even people with severe disabilities would have a better chance of living fuller lives and developing new skills in small homes rather than large, crowded institutions. By placing people in group and foster homes MORC helped to gradually reduce the number of people residing in institutions in Michigan. MORC, along with the Wayne County Community Living Agency, a State Department of Mental Health agency that MORC staff helped to establish, assisted in removing more than 5000 people from institutions in Michigan. Another 1000 people were able to avoid institutions all together, as they were placed directly into community homes. MORC's community placement efforts were often met with resistance from neighbors who owned property near proposed group homes. The issue generated a large amount of controversy and press coverage, as residents filed lawsuits or resorted to other methods in efforts to prevent group homes from being established in their neighborhoods.
For the first twenty-four years of its existence MORC operated as a state agency within the Michigan Department of Community Health. In September 1996 the state closed the MORC facility, but through contracts with local community mental health boards and authorities, MORC Inc. was authorized to continue to provide services as a nonprofit organization. MORC contracts with local community mental health boards and authorities and the Michigan Departments of Consumer and Industry Services and intermediate school districts and subcontracts with more than 150 nonprofit agencies within its communities.
For more information on MORC, INC., see their website at http://www.morcinc.com/htm/index.htm
The record group includes administrative and publicity material, material documenting resistance to community placement in Michigan, community placement legislation, the closing of the Plymouth Center Developmental Disabilities, and videocassettes.
Subjects:
Macomb-Oakland Regional Center.; Macomb County (Mich.); Mental health--Services--Michigan.; Mental health--Facilities--Michigan.; Mentally handicapped--Deinstitutionalization--Michigan.; Mentally handicapped--Michigan.; Mentally ill--Deinstitutionalization--Michigan.; Mentally ill--Michigan.; Oakland County (Mich.); Plymouth Center for Human Development (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Handicapped persons--Michigan.; Macomb-Oakland Regional Center.; Mental institutions--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Videocassettes.
- MORC Administrative and Publicity Material
  The MORC Administrative and Publicity Files series consists of material produced by the organization and material written about the organization. The series includes annual reports and meeting minutes as well as news releases, pamphlets, brochures and other publicity material produced by MORC. Also included is an extensive collection of newspaper clippings of articles related to MORC and the community placement movement in general.
  - Annual reports 1972-1977, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Foster Parent Recruitment Report 1981 (Box 1)
  - MORC staff meeting minutes 1972-1980, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Publications, Brochures, and Publicity Material
    - Transitions newsletter, 1973-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - News releases 1974-1982, undated (Box 1)
    - Brochures and pamphlets
      - Brochures and pamphlets 1970s (Box 1)
      - Foster care pamphlets 1970s (Box 1)
      - Information packet 2000 (Box 1)
    - MORC staff writings
      - Gerald Provencal articles
        - "Normalization: Means to an End," 1977 (Box 1)
        - "Security for Parents: Monitoring of Group Homes by Consumers," 1983 (Box 1)
        - "Community Based Facilities," undated (Box 1)
        - "Foster families: Macomb-Oakland Regional Center," undated (Box 1)
        - "Issues in the Process of Deinstitutionalization," undated (Box 1)
        - "Thoughts on Neighborhood Resistance," undated (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous staff writings and articles
        - "Apartment Programs for the Mentally Retarded: Myths and Realities," 1978 (Box 1)
        - "Ideas for Agency Activities to Gain Community Acceptance of Community Placement Programs and Clients," 1978 (Box 1)
        - Untitled paper on public hearings 1985 (Box 1)
        - "Questions for Video on Neighbor Concerns," (video script) 1986 (Box 1)
        - "Annotated Bibliography on Community Resistance and Acceptance of Community Residences for Persons with Mental Retardation," 1988 (Box 1)
        - "A Child's Birthright: To Live in a Family. A Vicarious Visit to Macomb-Oakland Regional Center," 1990 (Box 1)
        - "Gentle Teaching Approach Gaining at MORC," 1995 (Box 1)
        - "Community Placement and the Law: A Brief Overview of the 1970s," undated (Box 1)
        - "When Community Resistance is News," undated (Box 1)
        - "Progress of Residents in Community Placement Settings," undated (Box 1)
        - "Techniques in Notifying Neighbors," undated (Box 1)
        - "Resistance: The Proactive Approach," undated (Box 1)
    - Manuals and forms
      - Community Training Home Resource Manual 1980s (Box 1)
      - Recruitment of Foster Homes: An Instructional Manual of Foster Home Recruitment Technique 1980 (Box 1)
      - Manual for New Group Home Providers undated (Box 1)
      - MORC group home staff survey and questionnaire 1981 (Box 1)
      - Community notification plan form undated (Box 1)
      - MORC informational form "Who Do I Call?" undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous MORC material
    - Ceremonies and dedications
      - Ground breaking ceremony 1974 (Box 1)
      - Dedication 1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - MORC conferences 1981, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - AMORC monitors (parent monitoring group) 1980s (Box 1)
    - Tours of MORC facilities 1970s (Box 1)
    - Image of MORC duplex housing unit (Box 1)
    - Poster, "A Group Home is..." undated (Box 1)
  - Published material concerning MORC
    - Magazine and newspaper articles 1979-1990, undated (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings about MORC
      - MORC clippings 1971-1997, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - General clippings on community placement
        - Editorials, opinion columns and letters to the editor 1978-1989, undated, 13 folders (Box 2)
        - Feature articles 1969-1989 (primarily 1980s) (Box 2)
        - Federal legislation clippings 1980s (Box 2)
        - Community placement clippings book 1979-1981 (Box 2)
- Community Resistance Files
  The Community Resistance Files series documents the resistance to the placement of group homes in Michigan cities and towns. The series includes legal briefs and documents related to numerous community placement lawsuits, as well as newspaper clippings from cities and towns across Michigan, and correspondence, petitions, threats, and reports of vandalism and other incidents.
  - Law Suits
    - Michigan Law suits
      - Briefs and decisions
        - Bellarmine Hills v. Residential Systems 1978 (Box 2)
        - Brandon Township v. North Oakland Residential Services 1978, 1981, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Town of Bruce v. Department of Social Services 1983 (Box 2)
        - Craig et. al. v. Bossenbery 1982 (Box 2)
        - Greentree Civic Association v. Pignatiello 1983 (Box 2)
        - Livonia v. Department of Social Services 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Lleland Acres Homeowners Association v. R.T. Partnership 1981 (Box 2)
        - Malcolm et. al. v. Shamie et. al. 1978-1980, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - McMillan v. Iserman (Box 2)
        - Michigan Association for Retarded Citizens v. Smith, et. al. 1978 (Box 2)
        - Township of Oxford v. Department of Social Services 1982 (Box 2)
        - City of Sterling Heights v. Michigan Residential Services undated (Box 2)
        - Northfield Hills Homeowner Association v. Jack Blumekoff 1989 (Box 2)
      - Analysis of lawsuits
        - Livonia v. Department of Social Services and Greentree v. Pignatiello analysis 1985 (Box 2)
        - Summary and analysis of lawsuits (Box 2)
        - Legal response to overconcentration argument 1988 (Box 2)
    - Supreme Court decisions
      - Youngberg v. Romeo 1981 (Box 2)
      - Penhurst State School v. Halderman 1981 (Box 2)
  - Petitions, threats, and miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - MORC response to community resistance (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning community resistance in Michigan cities, towns and counties
    - Altmont (Box 2)
    - Avon Township (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 2)
    - Beverly Hills (Box 2)
    - Bloomfield Township (Box 2)
    - Bruce Township (Box 2)
    - Canton (Box 2)
    - Capac (Box 2)
    - Chesterfield (Box 2)
    - Commerce (Box 2)
    - Dearborn (Box 2)
    - Delta Township (Box 2)
    - Detroit (Box 2)
    - Farmington Hills (Box 2)
    - Gross Point (Box 2)
    - Harper Woods (Box 2)
    - Harrison Township (Box 2)
    - Highland Township (Box 2)
    - Holly Township (Box 2)
    - Independence Township (Box 2)
    - Lathrup Village (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Park (Box 2)
    - Livonia (Box 2)
    - Macomb (Box 2)
    - Milan (Box 2)
    - Milford (Box 2)
    - Mt. Clemens (Box 2)
    - Muskegon (Box 2)
    - Northville (Box 2)
    - Novi (Box 2)
    - Oak Park (Box 2)
    - Oakland County (Box 2)
    - Oakland Township (Box 2)
    - Orion (Box 2)
    - Oxford (Box 2)
    - Pleasant Ridge (Box 2)
    - Plymouth (Box 2)
    - Pontiac (Box 2)
    - Ray Township (Box 2)
    - Redford Township (Box 2)
    - Richmond (Box 2)
    - Rochester (Box 2)
    - Romeo (Box 2)
    - Romulus (Box 2)
    - Royal Oak (Box 2)
    - Saint Clair Shores (Box 2)
    - Shelby Township (Box 2)
    - Southfield (Box 2)
    - South Lyon (Box 2)
    - South Gate (Box 2)
    - Springfield Township (Box 2)
    - Sterling Heights (Box 2)
    - Sylvan Lake (Box 2)
    - Troy (Box 2)
    - Union Lake (Box 2)
    - Utica (Box 2)
    - Warner (Box 2)
    - Waterford (Box 2)
    - White Lake (Box 2)
    - Wixom (Box 2)
    - Woodhaven (Box 2)
    - Ypsilanti (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous statewide clippings (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Material
  The Miscellaneous series is a topical file of material not produced by MORC, but related to the issues of community placement in Michigan. The series includes publications and other material related to community placement of the disabled in Michigan. Two large subseries of material related to the Plymouth Center for Developmental Disabilities and the state of Michigan's policies for dealing with the developmentally disabled are included. The Plymouth Center subseries includes correspondence, reports, and clippings documenting allegations of abuse at and the closing of the Plymouth Center for Developmental Disabilities in 1979. The Michigan - state policies and legislation subseries consists of material produced by the state of Michigan and the Michigan Department of Mental Health regarding community placement and state services for the developmentally disabled. Included are planning documents, items concerning state legislation, and publications produced by the Department of Mental Health.
  - Association for Retarded Citizens/Oakland County booklet, "About Group Homes," 1986 (Box 3)
  - Association for Retarded Citizens/Oakland County "Resource Guide on Community Placement for Citizens with Mental Retardation," 1987 (Box 3)
  - Center on Human Rights, Syracuse Univ. "The Community Imperative: A Refutation of All Arguments in Support of Institutionalizing Anybody because of Mental Retardation," 1979 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Annual Conference of United Methodist Church letter in support of community placement 1980 (Box 3)
  - Joint Commission on the Accreditation of Hospitals, "Standards for the Mentally Retarded," 1971 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Protection and Advocacy Services 1989 (Box 3)
  - Michigan institution and nursing home closures 1997 (Box 3)
  - Michigan, state policies and legislation
    - Plans
      - State Developmental Disabilities Plan, Fiscal Year (1977-1978), 1979 update (Box 3)
      - State Developmental Disabilities Plan, Fiscal Year (1979-1980) (Box 3)
      - State Plan for Comprehensive Mental Health Services (1976), 1979-1980 update, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Legislation
      - Interim Report on Community Placement of Mentally Disabled Persons in Michigan, Joint Mental Health Oversight Committee, Senate Concurrent Resolution No. 44 July 1980 (Box 3)
      - Act No. 287 (adult foster care facilities licensing act) 1972 (Box 3)
      - Zoning laws and residential facilities 1976 (Box 3)
      - Regulation of adult foster homes (Act 218) 1979 (Box 3)
      - Children licensing rules (House Bill 6053) 1980 (Box 3)
      - Adult foster care licensing act (House Bill no. 4104) 1980 (Box 3)
      - Legislative attempts to curtail community placement 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Department of Mental Health material
      - "1981-1990; A Decade of Progress" publication (Box 3)
      - Article "Small Foster Homes Permitted in residential areas," 1977 (Box 3)
      - Map and list of state centers for the developmentally disabled 1983 (Box 3)
      - Department of Mental Health letter on group Home notification 1989 (Box 3)
      - Department of Mental Health Brochure, "Property Values: the Impact for Group Homes," 1980s (Box 3)
  - Plymouth Center Files
    - Histories and background 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Letters and memos concerning abuse allegations 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Milliken Correspondence 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Press releases 1978 (Box 3)
    - Clippings regarding abuse allegations (includes partial index), 1978 (Box 3)
  - Clippings regarding closure of the Plymouth Center 1970s, 1980s (Box 3)
  - United Nations "Declaration on the rights of mentally retarded persons," 1971 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous writing and publications
    - Miscellaneous journal and academic articles 1971-1999 (Box 3)
    - Unidentified "Mock Letter from Institution," 1971 (Box 3)
  - Photographs 2001 (Box 3)
- Videocassettes
  The Videocassettes series contains videos produced by MORC in efforts to promote and document the community placement movement. The series also includes tapes of news broadcasts related to the community placement issue, and footage of different Michigan state homes.
  - MORC produced videos
    - "Deep River," undated (Box 4)
    - "Monitoring with Love: AMORC Parent Monitoring," undated (Box 4)
    - "Our Family," undated (Box 4)
    - "The Run and Rally for Group Homes," 1981 (Box 4)
    - "Save Money and Make Money," undated (Box 4)
  - MORC personal training 2001 (Box 4)
  - Television broadcasts
    - "Homes for the Retarded", WXYZ-TV 1978 (Box 4)
    - "Focal Point", WTVS-TV56 undated (Box 4)
    - "Kelly and Company", Community Placement Debate WXYZ-TV 1980 (Box 4)
    - "Not On My Street", 60 Minutes, CBS-TV 1980 (Box 4)
    - "Rally at the Capitol", WXON-TV 1983 (Box 4)
    - "A Wind is Rising: Oakdale in the 60's," WJRP-TV undated (Box 4)
    - "Willowbrook: The Case Against the State," ABC news with Geraldo Rivera 1974 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified television shows and films
    - "A Fair Chance," (Coldwater State Hospital) 1950s (Box 4)
    - "A Way out of the Wilderness," Plymouth State Home 1966 (Box 4)
    - "The Often Forgotten," Plymouth Center 1978 (Box 4)
    - "Give me Liberty," Rally at the State Capitol 1980 (Box 4)
    - "Roses have Thorns," Kalamazoo State Hospital 1964 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous footage
    - Caro Regional Center 1950s (Box 4)
      no sound
    - Lapeer State Home, May Day Activities 1929 (Box 4)